In the 1600s, there were so many right whales in Cape Cod Bay
في القرن السابع عشر، كان هناك عدد كبير من الحيتان الصائبة في خليج كايب كود
off the east coast of the U.S.
قبالة الشاطئ الشرقي للولايات المتحدة .
that apparently you could walk across their backs
و التي يبدو أنه بمقدروك المشي على ظهورها
from one end of the bay to the other.
من بداية الخليج لآخره.
Today, they number in the hundreds, and they're endangered.
اليوم، أعدادها لا تتجاوز بعض مئات، وهي مهددة بالانقراض.
Like them, many species of whales saw their numbers drastically reduced
ومثلها ،أنواع كثيرة أخرى من الحيتان تعاني من التناقص الشديد في أعدادها
by 200 years of whaling,
بسبب 200 سنة من الاصطياد
where they were hunted and killed for their whale meat, oil and whale bone.
حيث يتم قنصها و قتلها من أجل لحمها زيوتها ،وعظامها.
We only have whales in our waters today
لدينا حيتان في مياهنا حالياً
because of the Save the Whales movement of the '70s.
بفضل حركة "أنقذ الحيتان" التي بدأت منذ السبعينات.
It was instrumental in stopping commercial whaling,
لقد كانت وسيلة لإيقاف اصطياد الحيتان لأغراض تجارية ،
and was built on the idea that if we couldn't save whales,
و كانت قائمة على فكرة أنّه لو لم يكن بمقدرتنا إنقاذ الحيتان،
what could we save?
فمن سننقذ؟
It was ultimately a test of our political ability
لقد كانت في النهاية امتحاناً لإمكانياتنا السياسية
to halt environmental destruction.
لوقف التدهور البيئي.
So in the early '80s, there was a ban on commercial whaling
وهكذا وفي بداية الثمانينات كان هناك فرض حظر على صيد الحيتان لأغراض تجارية
that came into force as a result of this campaign.
التي قويت نتيجةً لهذه الحملة.
Whales in our waters are still low in numbers, however,
وبالرغم من ذلك ، ما زالت أعداد الحيتان في مياهنا منخفضة
because they do face a range of other human-induced threats.
لأنّها تواجه أنواعاً أخرى من التهديدات البشرية.
Unfortunately, many people still think that whale conservationists like myself
للأسف، الكثير يعتقدون للآن أنّ المحافظين على الحيتان مثلي
do what we do only because these creatures are charismatic and beautiful.
يقومون بذلك فقط لأنّ تلك الكائنات جميلة و ذات كاريزما.
This is actually a disservice,
و هذا معتقد خاطئ،
because whales are ecosystem engineers.
لأنّ الحيتان هي بمثابة مهندسي النظام البيئي.
They help maintain the stability and health of the oceans,
إنّها تساهم في الحفاظ على صحة و توازن المحيطات،
and even provide services to human society.
بل و توفّر حتّى خدمات للمجتمع البشري.
So let's talk about why saving whales is critical
لنتحدث الآن عن سبب أهمية إنقاذ الحيتان
to the resiliency of the oceans.
لصمود المحيطات.
It boils down to two main things:
إنها تتلخص في أمرين رئيسيين:
whale poop and rotting carcasses.
براز الحيتان و جثثها المتعفنة.
As whales dive to the depths to feed and come up to the surface to breathe,
أثناء نزول الحيتان للأعماق لتتغذّى، و صعودها للأعلى للتنفّس،
they actually release these enormous fecal plumes.
تقوم بأخراج أعمدة كبيرة من البراز.
This whale pump, as it's called,
يسمّى ذلك ب"مضخة الحوت"،
actually brings essential limiting nutrients from the depths
وبفضله يتم نقل مغذّيات أساسية من الأعماق
to the surface waters where they stimulate the growth of phytoplankton,
إلى سطح المياه حيث تقوم بتحفيز نمو العوالق النباتية،
which forms the base of all marine food chains.
الذي تشكل قاعدة من كل السلاسل الغذائية البحرية.
So really, having more whales in the oceans pooping
بالتالي كلما زاد عدد الحيتان التي تتبرّز في المحيطات،
is really beneficial to the entire ecosystem.
كلّما كانت الفائدة أكثر للنظام البيئي بأكمله.
Whales are also known to undertake some of the longest migrations of all mammals.
الحيتان أيضاً معروفة بواحدة من أطول الهجرات بالنسبة للثديات.
Gray whales off America migrate 16,000 kilometers
الحيتان الرمادية تهاجر 16 ألف كم من أمريكا
between productive feeding areas and less productive calving, or birthing, areas
بين مناطق التغذية و مناطق الولادة
and back every year.
والعودة كلّ سنة.
As they do so, they transport fertilizer in the form of their feces
و أثناء ذلك، تقوم بنقل سماد في شكل فضلات
from places that have it to places that need it.
من مناطق تمتلكها إلى أخرى بحاجة إليها.
So clearly, whales are really important in nutrient cycling,
من الواضح إذن أن الحيتان مهمة جداً في السلسلة الغذائية ،
both horizontally and vertically, through the oceans.
على مستوى أفقي و عمودي، في المحيطات.
But what's really cool is that they're also really important after they're dead.
لكن الأمر الرائع حقاً هو كونها مهمة جداً حتى بعد موتها.
Whale carcasses are some of the largest form of detritus
جثث الحيتان تعتبر من إحدى أكبر المخلفات
to fall from the ocean's surface, and they're called whale fall.
التي تسقط من سطح المحيط وتسمّى ب"سقوط الحيتان".
As these carcasses sink,
بينما تغرق الجثث،
they provide a feast to some 400-odd species,
تقوم بتوفير وليمة لقرابة 400 نوعاً حيوانيّاً،
including the eel-shaped, slime-producing hagfish.
منها سمك الجريث المنتج للعاب .
So over the 200 years of whaling,
عبر 200 سنة من الاصطياد،
when we were busy killing and removing these carcasses from the oceans,
بينما كنّا منغمسين في القتل و استخراج الجثث من المحيطات،
we likely altered the rate and geographic distribution of these whale falls
فقد غيّرنا على الأرجح التوزّع الجغرافي و العددي لتساقط تلك الحيتان
that would descend into deep oceans,
التي كان من المفترض أن تنزل إلى أعماق المحيطات ،
and as a result, probably led to a number of extinctions
و نتيجة لذلك، تسبّب هذا على الأرجح في عدد من الانقراضات
of species that were most specialized
لعدد من الحيوانات التي كانت
and dependent on these carcasses for their survival.
تعتمد بصفة أساسية على هذه الجثث للبقاء.
Whale carcasses are also known to transport about 190,000 tons of carbon,
جثث الحيتان معروفة أيضا بنقلها لحوالي 190 ألف طن من الكربون
which is the equivalent of that produced
وهذا يعادل ما تنتجه
by 80,000 cars per year
80 ألف سيارة سنوياً
from the atmosphere to the deep oceans,
من الغلاف الجوي إلى أعماق المحيطات،
and the deep oceans are what we call "carbon sinks,"
و أعماق المحيطات التي تسمّى أيضاً "أحواض الكربون"
because they trap and hold excess carbon from the atmosphere,
لأنّها تحصر و تخزّن الكميات الزائدة من الكربون في الغلاف الجوي،
and therefore help to delay global warming.
مساهمة بالتالي في تأخير الاحتباس الحراري.
Sometimes these carcasses also wash up on beaches
أحياناً تصل تلك الجثث للشواطئ
and provide a meal to a number of predatory species on land.
موفّرة الطعام لبعض الحيوانات المفترسة البرية.
The 200 years of whaling was clearly detrimental
200 سنة من الصيد كانت مضرّة بوضوح
and caused a reduction in the populations of whales
فقد تسبّبت في نقصان أعداد الحيتان
between 60 to 90 percent.
ما بين 60 إلى 90%.
Clearly, the Save the Whales movement
من الواضح ،أن حركة "إنقاذ الحيتان"
was instrumental in preventing commercial whaling from going on,
كانت لها دور أساسي في منع استمرار الصيد التجاري للحيتان ،
but we need to revise this.
ولكن علينا مراجعة ذلك.
We need to address the more modern, pressing problems that these whales face
علينا مواجهة المشاكل والضغوطات المعاصرة التي تواجهها هذه الحيتان
in our waters today.
في مياهنا الآن.
Amongst other things, we need to stop them
من بين ذلك ، علينا إنقاذها
from getting plowed down by container ships when they're in their feeding areas,
من الاصطدام بسفن الشحن عند تواجدها في أمكان غذائها،
and stop them from getting entangled in fishing nets
و إنقاذها من العلوق بشبكات الصيد
as they float around in the ocean.
أثناء تجوالها بالمحيط.
We also need to learn to contextualize our conservation messages,
علينا أيضاً أن نتعلم تأطير رسائل الحفظ لدينا ،
so people really understand the true ecosystem value of these creatures.
حتّى يفهم الناس الأهمية البيئية الكبرى لهذه الكائنات.
So, let's save the whales again,
لذ ،دعونا ننقذ الحيتان مرة أخرى ،
but this time, let's not just do it for their sake.
لكن هذه المرة، لنقم بذلك ليس من أجلها فقط .
Let's also do it for ours.
و لكن من أجلنا ايضاً .
Thank you.
شكرا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)